Gabriel García Márquez is one of my favorite writers,
غابرييل غارسيا ماركيز واحد من كتابي المفضلين،
for his storytelling,
لسرده القصصي،
but even more, I think,
ولكني أعتقد أني أفضله أكثر
for the beauty and precision of his prose.
لجمال ودقة نثره.
And whether it's the opening line from "One Hundred Years of Solitude"
وسواء السطر الأول من "مائة عام من العزلة"
or the fantastical stream of consciousness
أو أسلوب سرد تيار الوعي الرائع
in "Autumn of the Patriarch,"
في "خريف البطريرك،"
where the words rush by,
حيث تتسارع الكلمات،
page after page of unpunctuated imagery
صفحة بعد صفحة كَسَيْلٍ من الصور
sweeping the reader along
تجتاح القارئ
like some wild river
كبعض أنهار البرية
twisting through a primal South American jungle,
الملتوية عبر الغابة البدائية بأمريكا الجنوبية،
reading Márquez is a visceral experience.
قراءة ماركيز تجربة عميقة.
Which struck me as particularly remarkable
الشيء الذي أذهلني
during one session with the novel
خلال القراءة الأولى للرواية هو
when I realized that I was being swept along
عندما وجدتني انجرفت مع
on this remarkable, vivid journey
هذه الرحلة الرائعة والأخاذة
in translation.
في الترجمة.
Now I was a comparative literature major in college,
لقد درست تخصص الأدب المقارن في الكلية،
which is like an English major,
وهو كتخصص اللغة الإنجليزية،
only instead of being stuck studying Chaucer for three months,
لكن بدل أن نقتصر على دراسة تشوسر ل 3 أشهر،
we got to read great literature in translation
فضلنا قراءة ترجمة الأعمال الأدبية الكبرى
from around the world.
من جميع أنحاء العالم.
And as great as these books were,
ومهما عظمت هذه الكتب،
you could always tell
يمكنكم دائماً القول
that you were getting close to the full effect.
أنكم ستحصلون على نفس تأثير الأصل.
But not so with Márquez
ولكن الأمر لا يكون كذلك مع ماركيز
who once praised his translator's versions
والذي أشاد بترجمات أعماله
as being better than his own,
على أنها أفضل من أعماله الأصلية،
which is an astonishing compliment.
وهي مجاملة رائعة منه.
So when I heard that the translator, Gregory Rabassa,
لدى عندما سمعت أن المترجم، غريغوري راباسا،
had written his own book on the subject,
قد كتب كتاب حول هذا الموضوع،
I couldn't wait to read it.
لم يسعني الانتظار حتى أقرأه.
It's called apropos of the Italian adage
وقد استوحى عنوانه من المقولة الإيطالية
that I lifted from his forward,
التي استعرتها من تمهيد الكتاب،
"If This Be Treason."
"إن كانت هذه خيانة."
And it's a charming read.
وهو كتاب رائع.
It's highly recommended for anyone who's interested
أوصي به بشدة كل من يهمه
in the translator's art.
فن الترجمة.
But the reason that I mention it
لكن الهدف من ذكري لهذا الكاتب
is that early on, Rabassa offers
هو أن راباسا قََدَّمَ منذ البداية
this elegantly simple insight:
فكرة بسيطة وجذابة:
"Every act of communication
"كل فعل للتواصل
is an act of translation."
هو فعل ترجمة ".
Now maybe that's been obvious to all of you for a long time,
لربما يكون هذا معروفا لديكم منذ وقت طويل
but for me,
لكن بالنسبة لي،
as often as I'd encountered
كلما واجهت
that exact difficulty on a daily basis,
الصعوبة ذاتها بشكل يومي،
I had never seen the inherent challenge of communication
لم يتجلى لي التحدي الخفي في التواصل
in so crystalline a light.
بهذا الوضوح.
Ever since I can remember
فكل ما أستطيع تذكره
thinking consciously about such things,
منذ أن بدأت في التفكير بتلك الأشياء،
communication has been my central passion.
كان التواصل مركز اهتمامي.
Even as a child,
حتى عندما كنت طفلا،
I remember thinking that what I really wanted most in life
أتذكر أن ما كنت أود حقا القيام به في الحياة
was to be able to understand everything
هو أن أكون قادرا على فهم كل شيء
and then to communicate it to everyone else.
لأبلغه لباقي الناس.
So no ego problems.
لا مشاكل لي مع الأنا.
It's funny, my wife, Daisy,
هذه قصة مضحكة، زوجتي ديزي،
whose family is littered with schizophrenics --
تنحدر من أسرة مصابة بانفصام الشخصية --
and I mean littered with them --
وأعني أن العديد من أفرادها مصابون --
once said to me, "Chris, I already have a brother who thinks he's God.
قالت لي مرة: "كريس، لدي أخ يعتقد أنه هو الله.
I don't need a husband who wants to be."
فلا أحتاج لزوج يريد أن يكون إلها أيضا".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Anyway, as I plunged through my 20s
على أية حال، بانغماسي في العشرينات من العمر
ever more aware of how unobtainable
أدركتُ أكثر فأكثر كيف أن
the first part of my childhood ambition was,
الجزء الأول من طموح طفولتي كان صعب المنال
it was that second part,
في الجزء الثاني،
being able to successfully communicate to others
وهو التمكن من تبليغ الآخرين بطريقة فعالة
whatever knowledge I was gaining,
أية معرفة قد أكتسبها،
where the futility of my quest really set in.
أدركت عدم جدوى طموحي.
Time after time,
مرة بعد أخرى،
whenever I set out to share some great truth
وكلما أردت تشارك بعض الحقائق الكبرى
with a soon-to-be grateful recipient,
مع متلق يكون أكثر امتنانا،
it had the opposite effect.
أحصل على رد فعل عكسي.
Interestingly, when your opening line of communication is,
المثير للاهتمام هو عندما تفتتح خطابك التواصلي ب،
"Hey, listen up,
"استمع،
because I'm about to drop some serious knowledge on you,"
لأني سأُنزل عليك بعض المعارف الخطيرة،"
it's amazing how quickly you'll discover
ستندهش بالسرعة التي ستكتشف بها
both ice and the firing squad.
الجليد ورصاص الإعدام.
Finally, after about 10 years
وأخيراً، وبعد حوالي 10 سنوات
of alienating friends and strangers alike,
من التحالف مع الأصدقاء والغرباء على حد سواء،
I finally got it,
أدركتُ أخيرا،
a new personal truth all my own,
حقيقة جديدة لنفسي،
that if I was going to ever communicate well with other people
هي إن كان علي تبليغ الأشخاص الأخرين
the ideas that I was gaining,
الأفكار التي اكتسبتها،
I'd better find a different way of going about it.
سيكون من الأفضل لي البحث عن طريقة أخرى لذلك.
And that's when I discovered comedy.
وكانت اللحظة التي اكتشفت فيها الكوميديا.
Now comedy travels along a distinct wavelength
الخطاب الكوميدي ينتقل على موجة مميزة
from other forms of language.
عكس الأشكال الأخرى للغة.
If I had to place it on an arbitrary spectrum,
إذا وجب علي تحديد موضعها بشكل اعتباطي،
I'd say it falls somewhere
سأقول أنها تقع في مكان ما
between poetry and lies.
بين الشعر والأكاذيب.
And I'm not talking about all comedy here,
وأنا لا أتحدث عن كل الكوميديا هنا،
because, clearly, there's plenty of humor
فمن الواضح أن هناك وفرة من الكوميديا
that colors safely within the lines of what we already think and feel.
وهذه الألوان الكوميدية تبقى بأمان بين ما نعتقده ونشعر به مسبقا.
What I want to talk about
ما أود التحدث عنه
is the unique ability that the best comedy and satire has
هي القدرة الفريدة لدى الكوميديا والسخرية الحقيقيتين
at circumventing our ingrained perspectives --
في التحايل على وجهات النظر المتجذرة لدينا --
comedy as the philosopher's stone.
الكوميديا في دور حجر الفيلسوف.
It takes the base metal of our conventional wisdom
فهي تأخذ المادة الأولية لحِكْمَتِنَا العامة
and transforms it through ridicule
وتحولها من خلال السخرية
into a different way of seeing
إلى طريقة مختلفة للنظر
and ultimately being in the world.
والعيش بالعالم.
Because that's what I take
لأن هذا ما فهمته
from the theme of this conference: Gained in Translation.
من موضوع هذا المؤتمر: مُكتسب من الترجمة.
That it's about communication
إن تعلق الأمر بالتواصل
that doesn't just produce greater understanding
فإنه لا يقدم فهما جيدا
within the individual,
للفرد فقط،
but leads to real change.
ولكن يؤدي لتغيير حقيقي.
Which in my experience means communication
الشيء الذي يمثل التواصل، حسب خبرتي،
that manages to speak to and expand
هو الشخص القادر على التحدث وتوسيع
our concept of self-interest.
مفهومنا عن مصلحتنا الشخصية.
Now I'm big on speaking to people's self-interest
اليوم أصبحت متحدثا كبيرا عن المصلحة الشخصية للناس
because we're all wired for that.
لأننا خُلِقْنَا لذلك.
It's part of our survival package,
إنها جزء من معدات النجاة خاصتنا،
and that's why it's become so important for us,
وهذا ما يجعلها مهمة بالنسبة لنا،
and that's why we're always listening at that level.
ولهذا السبب نحن دائماً نصغي عند هذا المستوى.
And also because that's where,
كما أنه في هذه المرحلة،
in terms of our own self-interest,
من خلال مصلحتنا الشخصية،
we finally begin to grasp
نبدأ أخيراً بإدراك
our ability to respond, our responsibility
قدرتنا على تكييف مفهوم مسؤوليتنا
to the rest of the world.
لبقية العالم.
Now as to what I mean by the best comedy and satire,
بالعودة لما أعنيه بأفضل كوميديا وسخرية،
I mean work that comes first and foremost
أقصد أن أي عمل يصدر في المقام الأول وفي الغالب
from a place of honesty and integrity.
عن الصدق والنزاهة.
Now if you think back
إن عدتم بالذاكرة
on Tina Fey's impersonations on Saturday Night Live
لتشخيص تينا فاي في برنامجها "Saturday Night Live"
of the newly nominated vice presidential candidate
للمرشحة المعينة حديثا لمنصب نائب الرئيس
Sarah Palin,
سارة بالين،
they were devastating.
كان مدمرا.
Fey demonstrated far more effectively than any political pundit
أظهرت فاي بفعالية أكثر من أي خبير سياسي
the candidate's fundamental lack of seriousness,
نقص الجدية الكبير للمرشحة،
cementing an impression
من خلال تقويت الانطباع
that the majority of the American public still holds today.
الذي لا يزال لدى غالبية الرأي العام الأميركي اليوم.
And the key detail of this
والتفصيل الرئيسي لهذا
is that Fey's scripts weren't written by her
هو أن فاي لا تكتب ما تقوله بنفسها
and they weren't written by the SNL writers.
ولا يكتبه لها كُتَّاب برنامجها SNL.
They were lifted verbatim
بل اقتبسوه كلمة كلمة
from Palin's own remarks.
من التصريحات الخاصة ببالين .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Here was a Palin impersonator
كان هذا تشخيص لبالين
quoting Palin word for word.
نُقِل كلمة كلمة عن بالين.
Now that's honesty and integrity,
هذا ما يعنيه الصدق والنزاهة،
and it's also why Fey's performances
وهو أيضا السبب في أن تشخيص فاي
left such a lasting impression.
ترك انطباعا دائم.
On the other side of the political spectrum,
من الجانب الآخر للطيف السياسي،
the first time that I heard Rush Limbaugh
منذ المرة الأولى التي سمعت فيها "راش ليمبو"
refer to presidential hopeful John Edwards as the Breck girl
يشير إلى رغبة جون إدواردز بالترشح للرئاسة كإشهار شامبو نسائي
I knew that he'd made a direct hit.
علمت أنه سدد ضربة مباشرة.
Now it's not often that I'm going to associate
فمن الناذر أن أجمع
the words honesty and integrity with Limbaugh,
كلمتي الصدق والنزاهة مع ليمبو،
but it's really hard to argue with that punchline.
ولكن من الصعب حقا معارضة لب تلك النكتة.
The description perfectly captured
كان الوصف مثاليا
Edwards' personal vanity.
لمظهر إدواردز الشخصي.
And guess what?
واحزروا ماذا؟
That ended up being the exact personality trait
لقد أصبحت في النهاية أدق سِمَة تصف شخصيته
that was at the core of the scandal that ended his political career.
خلال غمرة الفضيحة التي أنهت حياته السياسية.
Now The Daily Show with John Stewart
إن برنامج "ديلي شو" مع جون ستيوارت
is by far the most --
هو الأكثر--
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
it's by far the most well-documented example
هو المثال الأكثر توثيقاً
of the effectiveness of this kind of comedy.
حول فعالية هذا النوع من الكوميديا.
Survey after survey,
دراسة بعد آخرى،
from Pew Research to the Annenberg Center for Public Policy,
من مركز بيو للدراسات حتى مركز انينبرغ للسياسة العامة،
has found that Daily Show viewers are better informed about current events
كلهم وجدوا أن مشاهدي برنامج "ديلي شو" هم الأفضل اطلاعاً على الأحداث الجارية
than the viewers of all major network and cable news shows.
بالمقارنة بمشاهدي جميع القنوات الكبرى والبرامج الإخبارية على الكابل.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Now whether this says more
إذا كان هذا يخبرنا المزيد
about the conflict between integrity and profitability
عن صراع النزاهة والربحية
of corporate journalism
لصحافة الشركات
than it does about the attentiveness of Stewart's viewers,
أكثر من اهتمام مشاهدي ستيوارت،
the larger point remains
فإن النقطة الأهم تبقى
that Stewart's material
أن المادة الإعلامية لستيوارت
is always grounded in a commitment to the facts --
تستند دائماً على الوقائع --
not because his intent is to inform. It's not.
وليس لأنها تريد فقط تبليغ الخبر. إنها ليست كذلك.
His intent is to be funny.
فهدفها هو أن تكون مضحكة.
It just so happens that Stewart's brand of funny
ويبدو أن كوميديا ستيوارت
doesn't work unless the facts are true.
لا تعمل إلا إذا كانت تستند على وقائع حقيقية.
And the result is great comedy
والنتيجة كوميديا رائعة
that's also an information delivery system
وهذا أيضا نظام لإيصال المعلومات
that scores markedly higher in both credibility and retention
يسجل معدلا مرتفعا فيما يخص المصداقية والتحفظ
than the professional news media.
قياسا بوسائل الإعلام المحترفة.
Now this is doubly ironic
وهذا مثير للسخرية على صعيدين
when you consider that what gives comedy its edge
إن اعتبرتم أن ما يعطي للكوميديا
at reaching around people's walls
قدرتها على تجاوز دفاعات الناس ضد الضحك
is the way that it uses deliberate misdirection.
هي الطريقة التي تستخدمها بعمد للتوجيه الخاطئ.
A great piece of comedy is a verbal magic trick,
فإن مسرحية كوميدية كبيرة هي خدعة سحرية كلامية،
where you think it's going over here
فعندما تعتقد أنها ستأخذ هذا الاتجاه
and then all of a sudden you're transported over here.
تجرك فجأة بالاتجاه الأخر.
And there's this mental delight
وهناك تلك المتعة الداخلية
that's followed by the physical response of laughter,
متبوعة بالضحك كرد فعل لذلك،
which, not coincidentally,
والتي تطلق، بالصدفة،
releases endorphins in the brain.
الأندورفين في المخ.
And just like that, you've been seduced
وهكذا تجد نفسك
into a different way of looking at something
تنظر إلى الأمور بطريقة أخرى
because the endorphins have brought down your defenses.
لأن الأندروفين أسقط دفاعاتكم ضد الضحك.
This is the exact opposite
وهذا عكس طريقة
of the way that anger and fear and panic,
الغضب والخوف والذعر،
all of the flight-or-fight responses, operate.
فجميع ردود الفعل عن الطيران أو القتال تعمل.
Flight-or-fight releases adrenalin,
الطيران أو القتال تطلق الأدرينالين،
which throws our walls up sky-high.
الذي يرفع من دفاعاتنا إلى أعلى مستوى.
And the comedy comes along,
وتأتي الكوميديا فتتمكن من،
dealing with a lot of the same areas
التعامل مع نفس المجالات
where our defenses are the strongest --
حيث دفاعاتنا هي الأقوى --
race, religion, politics, sexuality --
العرق، الدين، السياسة، والجنس --
only by approaching them through humor instead of adrenalin,
فبالتعامل معها من خلال الضحك فقط بدلاً من الأدرينالين،
we get endorphins
نحصل على الأندروفين
and the alchemy of laughter turns our walls into windows,
لتحول كيمياء الضحك لدينا الجدران إلى نوافذ،
revealing a fresh and unexpected point of view.
لتكشف عن وجهة نظر جديدة وغير متوقعة.
Now let me give you an example from my act.
اسمحوا لي أن اضرب لكم مثالاً من قانونِ بَلدي.
I have some material
لدي بعض المواد
about the so-called radical gay agenda,
حول ما يسمى بالبرنامج الراديكالي للمثليين جنسيا،
which starts off by asking,
والذي يبدأ بالتساؤل،
how radical is the gay agenda?
ما مدى راديكالية برنامج المثليين جنسيا؟
Because from what I can tell, the three things gay Americans seem to want most
لأنه حسب ما أعرفه، يبدو أن الأمور 3 التي يطالب بها المثليين الأمريكيين بشدة
are to join the military, get married and start a family.
هي الانضمام إلى الجيش والزواج وتأسيس أسرة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Three things I've tried to avoid my entire life.
ثلاثة أشياء حاولت تجنبها كل حياتي.
Have at it you radical bastards. The field is yours.
خذوها أيها الأوغاد الراديكاليين. الساحة لكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And that's followed by these lines
والتي تتبعها هذه الأسطر
about gay adoption:
حول تبني المثليين جنسيا:
What is the problem with gay adoption?
ما هي المشكلة في تبني المثليين جنسيا؟
Why is this remotely controversial?
لماذا يعتبر هذا الأمر مثيرا للجدل؟
If you have a baby and you think that baby's gay,
إن كان لديك طفل وتظن أنه مثلي جنسيا،
you should be allowed to put it up for adoption.
يجب أن يكون لك الحق في إعطائه للتبني.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You have given birth to an abomination.
لقد أنجبتم رجسا.
Remove it from your household.
أبعده عن منزلك.
Now by taking the biblical epithet "abomination"
من خلال استعارة نعت الكتاب المقدس "رجس"
and attaching it to the ultimate image of innocence, a baby,
ووضعه مع الصورة المثالية للبراءة، وهي الطفل،
this joke short circuits the emotional wiring
هذه النكتة الصغيرة تسبب تماس كهربائي بالنظام العاطفي
behind the debate
وراء النقاش
and it leaves the audience with the opportunity, through their laughter,
وتترك الفرصة للجمهور، من خلال الضحك،
to question its validity.
للتشكيك في شرعيته.
Misdirection isn't the only trick
التوجيه الخاطئ ليس هو الخدعة الوحيدة
that comedy has up its sleeve.
في جُعْبَة الكوميديا.
Economy of language
اقتصاد اللغة
is another real strong suit of great comedy.
هي نقطة قوة أخرى لدى الكوميديا الحقيقية.
There are few phrases
ليس هناك الكثير من العبارات
that pack a more concentrated dose of subject and symbol
القادرة على تجميع العديد من المواضيع والرموز المركزة بجرعة واحدة
than the perfect punchline.
أكثر من نهايةٍ مميزةٍ لنكتة ما.
Bill Hicks -- and if you don't know his work,
بيل هيكس -- إن كنتم لا تعرفون عمله،
you should really Google him --
يجب عليكم البحث عنه في جوجل --
Hicks had a routine
كان هيكس يقدم عرضا حول
about getting into one of those childhood bragging contests on the playground,
الدخول في منافسة للتفاخر بين الأطفال بساحة المدرسة،
where finally the other kid says to him,
حيث يقول له الطفل الأخر في النهاية،
"Huh? Well my dad can beat up your dad,"
"ها؟ يستطيع والدي أن يشبع والدك ضربا، "
to which Hicks replies,
فيجيب هيكس،
"Really? How soon?"
"حقا؟ متى؟ "
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's an entire childhood
وهذه هي الطفولة برمتها
in three words.
في ثلاث كلمات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Not to mention what it reveals
وناهيك عما تكشف عنه
about the adult who's speaking them.
حول الكبار الذين يتحدثون بتلك الكلمات.
And one last powerful attribute
وكَسِمَة قوية أخيرة
that comedy has as communication
للكوميديا في التواصل
is that it's inherently viral.
هي أنها ذات طبيعة فيروسية.
People can't wait
الناس على أحر من الجمر
to pass along that new great joke.
لنقل أخر نكتة.
And this isn't some new phenomenon of our wired world.
وهي ليست ظاهرة جديدة لعالمنا العنكبوتي.
Comedy has been crossing country
دائما ما تعبر الكوميديا البلد
with remarkable speed
بسرعة مدهشة
way before the Internet, social media,
قبل الإنترنت، ووسائل الإعلام الاجتماعية،
even cable TV.
وحتى قنوات الكابل.
Back in 1980
بالعودة لعام 1980
when comedian Richard Pryor accidentally set himself on fire
عندما أشعل الكوميدي ريتشارد بريور بالخطأ في نفسه النار
during a freebasing accident,
خلال تعاطيه المخدرات،
I was in Los Angeles the day after it happened
اليوم التالي للحادث كنت في لوس أنجلوس
and then I was in Washington D.C. two days after that.
وبعد ذلك بيومين كنت في واشنطن العاصمة.
And I heard the exact same punchline on both coasts --
وسمعت النكت نفسها على كلا الساحلين --
something about the Ignited Negro College Fund.
شيئا عن الصندوق الجامعي للأَسْوَدِ المحترق.
Clearly, it didn't come out of a Tonight Show monologue.
ومن الواضح أنه لم يصدر عن مونولوج برنامج "تونايت شو".
And my guess here -- and I have no research on this --
وأظن -- وأنا لم أبحث في الأمر --
is that if you really were to look back at it and if you could research it,
أنه لو عدتم بالزمن وقمتم بالبحث،
you'd find out that comedy
ستجدون أن الكوميديا
is the second oldest viral profession.
هي ثاني أقدم مهنة ذات طبيعة فيروسية.
First there were drums
فهناك في المرتبة الأولى الطبول
and then knock-knock jokes.
ثم نكتة - من الطارق؟.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But it's when you put all of these elements together --
لكن بوضع جميع هذه العناصر معا --
when you get the viral appeal of a great joke
عند إضفاء ذلك السحر الفيروسي على النكتة الجيدة
with a powerful punchline
ذات النهاية القوية
that's crafted from honesty and integrity,
التي تَنْهَلُ من الصدق والنزاهة،
it can have a real world impact
يمكن أن يكون لها تأثير عالمي حقيقي
at changing a conversation.
لتغيير حوار ما.
Now I have a close friend, Joel Pett,
لدي صديق مقرّب، جويل بيت،
who's the editorial cartoonist
وهو رسام كاريكاتير
for the Lexington Herald-Leader.
لجريدة لكسنغتون هيرالد - ليدر.
And he used to be the USA Today Monday morning guy.
واعتاد أن يكون نجم صبيحة الإثنين بجريدة "يو إس إي توداي".
I was visiting with Joel
كنت في زيارة لجويل بنهاية الأسبوع
the weekend before the Copenhagen conference on climate change opened
التي سبقت افتتاح مؤتمر كوبنهاغن المتعلق بتغير المناخ
in December of 2009.
في كانون الأول/ديسمبر 2009.
And Joel was explaining to me
وقد شرح لي جويل
that, because USA Today
أنه، بما أن جريدة "يو إس إي توداي"
was one of America's four papers of record,
كانت واحدة من أربع جرائد الأكثر انتشارا،
it would be scanned by virtually everyone in attendance at the conference,
وأنها سَتُقرأ تقريبا من جميع المشاركين بالمؤتمر،
which meant that, if he hit it out of the park with his cartoon
مما يعني أنه إن حقق نجاحا كبيرا برسومه
on Monday, the opening day of the conference,
يوم الاثنين أي يوم افتتاح المؤتمر،
it could get passed around
فإنها ستمر
at the highest level among actual decision-makers.
على أعلى مستوى لصناع القرار.
So we started talking about climate change.
لذلك بدأنا نتحدث عن تغير المناخ.
And it turned out that Joel and I
وتصادف أن جويل وأنا
were both bothered by the same thing,
كنا قلقين من نفس الشيء،
which was how so much of the debate
وهو أن جزء كبير من النقاش
was still focused on the science
كان مركزا على العلوم
and how complete it was or wasn't,
ومدى كمالها في هذا المجال،
which, to both of us,
والذي، كان في نظرنا،
seems somewhat intentionally off point.
يبدو إلى حد ما محدود.
Because first of all, there's this false premise
فأولاً وقبل كل شيء، هناك هذا المنطلق الخاطئ
that such a thing as complete science exists.
أن شيئا من قبيل العلم الكامل موجود.
Now Governor Perry of my newly-adopted state of Texas
بيري حاكم ولاية تكساس التي تبنيتها حديثا
was pushing this same line this past summer
قد روج لنفس الفكرة في الصيف الماضي
at the beginning of his oops-fated campaign
عند بداية حملته -عفوا- المنكوبة
for the Republican presidential nomination,
للترشح على رأس الحزب الجمهوري من أجل الرئاسة،
proclaiming over and over that the science wasn't complete
ليعلن مرارا وتكرارا أن العلم لم يكن كاملا
at the same time that 250
بينما كانت 250
out of 254 counties in the state of Texas
من أصل 254 مقاطعة في ولاية تكساس
were on fire.
تحترق.
And Perry's policy solution
وكان الحل السياسي لبيري
was to ask the people of Texas
هو الطلب من سكان تكساس
to pray for rain.
الصلاة من أجل سقوط المطر.
Personally, I was praying for four more fires
شخصيا، سأصلي لأربعة حرائق أخرى
so we could finally complete the damn science.
حتى يتمكن العلم اللعين أخيرا من أن يكون كاملا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But back in 2009,
ولكن بالعودة لعام 2009،
the question Joel and I kept turning over and over
فإن المسألة التي ما فتئنا جويل وأنا نعود إليها مرارا وتكرارا
was why this late in the game
كانت السبب في هذا التأخر
so much energy was being spent talking about the science
فقد أنفقنا الكثير من الطاقة للحديث عن العلم
when the policies necessary to address climate change
في حين أن السياسات الضرورية لمعالجة تغير المناخ
were unequivocally beneficial for humanity in the long run
كانت بلا شك مفيدة للبشرية على المدى البعيد
regardless of the science.
بغض النظر عن العلم.
So we tossed it back and forth until Joel came up with this.
لم نتوقف عن تقليب الموضوع عندما آتى جويل بهذه.
Cartoon: "What if it's a big hoax and we create a better world for nothing?"
الرسوم: "ماذا لو كانت خدعة كبيرة بينما نحن نحاول خلق عالم أفضل لأجل لا شيء؟"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You've got to love that idea.
لقد أعجبتكم الفكرة.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
How about that? How about we create a better world for nothing?
ماذا عن هذا؟ ماذا عن كوننا نخلق عالم أفضل لأجل لا شيء؟
Not for God, not for country, not for profit --
ليس من أجل الله، أو البلد، أو الربح --
just as a basic metric for global decision-making.
فقط كوحدة لقياس عملية صناعة القرار العالمي.
And this cartoon hit the bull's eye.
وقد أدت هذه الرسوم المبتغى.
Shortly after the conference was over,
بعد وقت قصير من انتهاء المؤتمر،
Joel got a request for a signed copy
تلقى جويل طلبا من رئيس وكالة حماية البيئة في واشنطن
from the head of the EPA in Washington
للحصول على على نسخة موقعة منه
whose wall it now hangs on.
كي يتم تعليقها بالوكالة.
And not long after that, he got another request for a copy
وبعد فترة قصيرة، تلقى طلبا آخر من رئيس
from the head of the EPA in California
وكالة حماية البيئة في كاليفورنيا للحصول على نسخة
who used it as part of her presentation
استخدمتها كجزء من عرضها
at an international conference on climate change
في مؤتمر دولي حول تغير المناخ
in Sacramento last year.
في سكرامنتو العام الماضي.
And it didn't stop there.
ولم يتوقف الأمر عند ذلك.
To date, Joel's gotten requests from over 40 environmental groups,
فحتى الآن، حصل جويل على طلبات من أكثر من 40 مجموعة لحماية البيئية،
in the United States, Canada and Europe.
في الولايات المتحدة وكندا وأوروبا.
And earlier this year,
وفي بداية هذا العام،
he got a request from the Green Party in Australia
حصل على طلب من "حزب الخضر" في أستراليا
who used it in their campaign
الذي استخدمه في حملته
where it became part of the debate
حيث أصبح طرفا في النقاش
that resulted in the Australian parliament
الذي أدى إلى تبني البرلمان الأسترالي
adopting the most rigorous carbon tax regime
لنظام ضريبة الكربون الأشد حزما
of any country in the world.
في العالم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
That is a lot of punch
وهذه أهداف كثيرة حققت
for 14 words.
بالنسبة ل 14 كلمة.
So my suggestion to those of you out here
لذا، فاقتراحي لكم جميعا هنا
who are seriously focused on creating a better world
أنتم الجادين والمركزين على إيجاد عالم أفضل
is to take a little bit of time each day
أن تأخذوا قليلاً من الوقت كل يوم
and practice thinking funny,
وممارسة التفكير المضحك،
because you might just find the question that you've been looking for.
لأنك قد تجد السؤال الذي كنت تبحث عنه.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)